Guide to the Charles Recht Papers TAM.176
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Charles Recht Papers
1907-1976
TAM.176
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.75 linear feet in one record carton.
Charles C. Recht (1887-1965) graduated from New York University Law School in 1910. During and after World War I, he served as general counsel for the New York Bureau of Legal Advice. Recht represented many radicals who faced deportation, served as an officer of the Communist-associated American Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, and from 1921-1933, he served as the official representative of the Soviet Union's interests in the United States. He wrote widely on law, politics, theater and Jewish history, and published two novels and a book of poems. His wife, Aristine Munn Recht, was Dean of Women at NYU's Washington Square College. The majority of the collection is made up of his published and unpublished writings.
Recht, Charles.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Materials found in repository, but were likely a gift of John Munn Recht (son of Charles Recht) in 1995. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1995.006, 1995.008 and NPA.2005.023.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Charles C. Recht (1887-1965) was born in Bohemia to Jewish parents, emigrated to the United States at age thirteen, and graduated from New York University Law School in 1910. He served as general counsel for the New York Bureau of Legal Advice, which provided free legal service to men who resisted the World War I era draft laws. Recht also represented many radicals who faced deportation at that time, and later served as an officer of a the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (ACPFB). ACPFB was affiliated with the Communist Party USA, but Recht was never a party member. After Ludwig Martens was deported in 1921, Recht officially represented Soviet interests in the United States until 1933, when diplomatic relations were established. Recht published two novels, Rue with a Difference(1924) and Babylon on Hudson(1932), and a book of poems, Manhattan Made(1930). He also translated the work of August Strindberg and other playwrights, and wrote widely on law, politics, theater and Jewish history. His wife, Aristine Munn Recht, a physician, was at one time Dean of Women at NYU's Washington Square College.
Scope and Content Note
The brief biographical series contains some personal correspondence, memorabilia, photographs and obituaries. The bulk of the collection consists of Recht's unpublished writings, including: A World to Win, an autobiography (along with several autobiographical fragments) covering Recht's life through the early 1930s, including his travels throughout the Soviet Union; Selector H. One, a satirical science fiction novel written in the 1940s; and an untitled and incomplete novel largely about "Ernest Strohman," an immigrant of Bohemian origin. Other writings include various poems, two untitled plays dealing with Jewish history, and an early (1907) pamphlet-length non-fiction manuscript, The Bohemian in America. The published writings consist of several articles dealing with civil rights and Jewish history.
Arrangement
Organized into two series:
Series I: Biographical
Series II: Writings
Subseries A: Published Writings
Subseries B: Unpublished
Sub-subseries 1: Autobiographical Typescript, A World To Win
Sub-subseries 2: Other Unpublished Writings
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
Related Archival Materials note
American Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born Records (TAM 086)
New York Bureau of Legal Advice Records (TAM 044)
American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born.; Recht, Charles.; American literature |x Jewish authors.; Communists |z United States |v Biography.; Communists |z United States.; Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Obituaries.; Soviet Union |x Description and travel.
- Series I: Biographical, 1906-1976
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, obituaries of Recht, and photographs. The photographs are made up of a double-sided scrapbook page of photographs from the 1920s and larger black-and-white photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Writings
  This series contains both published articles and unpublished manuscripts by Recht.
  - Subseries A: Published Writings, 1918-1936
    This subseries contains his published articles, mostly related to his work with immigrants.
    - "The Chinese Jew - A Footnote" ( The American Hebrew), Oct 23, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Czechs and the Jews: Past and Present" ( The Menorah Journal), Dec 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Glory That Was" (Reprint from: Let the People Vote on War magazine), Apr 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Historical Landmarks of the Czechs" ( The Public: A Journal of Democracy), Aug 24, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "If Europe Were Modern Minded" ( The Modern World), Jan 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Right of Asylum ( New York: The Social Economic Foundation), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Unpublished Writings
    This subseries mostly contains Recht's unpublished autobiography, A World to Win: The Autobiography of a Non-Conformist. the manuscript is broken up into chapters, containing handwritten notes and drafts. The subseries also contains publishing correspondence and other materials. Other manuscripts include "The Bohemian in America;" a manuscript possibly titled "Ernest Strohman;" an article titled "Walt Whitman in Memoriam;" two plays, one set in the Near East, the other in 18th-19th century Europe; poetry; and three variants of his science-fiction novel, Selector H. One.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Autobiographical Typescript, ( A World To Win), undated, 1907-1947
      - Chapter Outlines, Introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Chapter 1: Transplantation, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Chapter 2: Striking Roots, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Chapter 3: English Becomes Basic, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Chapter 4: First Case, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Chapter 5: It Shouldn't Happen to a Dog, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Chapter 6: Marriage & War, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Chapter 7: Nov 7, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Chapter 8: Getting Reputation, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Chapter 9: Unrest, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Chapter 10: Red Special, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Chapter 11: Omsk Mutiny, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Chapter 12: Soviet Bureau, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Chapter 13: Palmer's Putsch, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Chapter 14: Groans From Omsk, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Chapter 15: The Most Cross Examined Man, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Chapter 17: Genoa, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Chapter 18: Russian Volunteer Fleet, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Chapter 19: Eastward From Paris, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Chapter 20: Litvinoff and Recognition, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Chapter, Unnumbered: Biro-Bidjan, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Miscellaneous Autobiographical Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Publishing Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Other Unpublished Writings, undated, 1907-1947
      - The Bohemian in America, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Fiction: "Ernest Strohman?", undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Non-Fiction, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Play (untitled fragment, set in ancient Near East), undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Play (untitled fragment, set in Europe, circa 18th-19th century), undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Selector H. One (variant "1"), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Selector H. One (variant "2"), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - Selector H. One (variant "3"), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 42)